Guide to the William Fowler Hopson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Fowler Hopson papers
1865-1941
MS 287
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
12
(32 boxes, 1 volume)
Correspondence, genealogical material, account books, and miscellaneous papers of William F. Hopson. The collection contains papers related to his many club activities, including the Acorn Club of Connecticut, Grolier Club, and Rowfant Club of Cleveland.
Hopson, William Fowler, 1849-1935
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. W. F. Hopson, 1940.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. General Correspondence. II. Invitations. III. Topical Files. IV. Oversize.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
William Fowler Hopson (1849-1935): artist and engraver; in 1870 moved to New York City to work as book engraver; in 1872 moved to New Haven, Ct., in partnership with Roger Sherman as professional engravers; engraver of many bookplates.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, genealogical material, account books, and miscellaneous papers of William F. Hopson. The collection contains papers related to his many club activities, including the Acorn Club of Connecticut, Grolier Club, and Rowfant Club of Cleveland.
Art; Account books; Engravers; Hopson, William Fowler, 1849-1935; Hopson family; Acorn Club of Connecticut; Grolier Club; Rowfant Club (Cleveland, Ohio)
- General Correspondence, 1802-1944; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Ab-Al, 1907-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Acorn Club, 1900-1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Allen, Charles Dexter, 1890-1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
  - Am-Az, 1886-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9-13)
  - American Bookplate Association and American Antiquarian Society, 1904-1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Autograph letters, 1814-1918 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - B-Barnett, 1894-1935 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Barrie-Buttnick, 1819-1944 (Box 2, Folder 18-25)
  - Baer, Carlyle S., 1924-1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Bates, Albert C., 1888-1934, undated (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Blatchford, Ellen, 1903-1928, undated (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - C, 1866-1940, undated (Box 3, Folder 32-37)
  - Carver, Clifford N., 1913-1915 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Cheney, Sheldon, 1802-1935, undated (Box 3, Folder 39-42)
  - Clubb of Odd Volumes, 1906-1935, undated (Box 3, Folder 43-45)
  - Cole, Timothy, 1901-1931 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Cram, George W., 1894-1895, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - D, 1835-1942 (Box 4, Folder 48-51)
  - Deane, Ruthven, 1910-1932 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Dixson, Zella A., 1902-1904 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - E, 1897-1935 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Evans, Clara T., 1913-1935, undated (Box 4, Folder 55-56)
  - Evans, John W., 1870-1943, undated (Box 4, Folder 57-64)
  - F, 1887-1933 (Box 5, Folder 65-67)
  - Fowler, H. Alfred, 1911-1934, undated (Box 5, Folder 68-70)
  - French, E.D., 1894-1906, undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - G, 1898-1938 (Box 5, Folder 72-75)
  - Garnett, R., 1902-1906, undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Godard, George S., 1900-1935, undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Grolier Club, 1890-1935, undated (Box 6, Folder 78-90)
  - H, 1847-1939, undated (Box 7, Folder 91-95)
  - Harper, H.H., 1901-1935, undated (Box 7, Folder 96-102)
  - Hopson, William F., 1898-1934, undated (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - I, 1905-1935 (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - Inis, William M., 1914-1935, undated (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - J, 1901-1935 (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Joline, Adrian H., 1897-1908 (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - K, 1890-1935 (Box 8, Folder 108-109)
  - Keogh, Andrew, 1913-1932, undated (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - L, 1894-1935 (Box 8, Folder 111-115)
  - Linton, Ellen Wade, 1873-1932, undated (Box 8, Folder 116)
  - Linton, W.J., 1839-1928 (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - Linton, W.J., 1929-1938, undated (Box 9, Folder 118-119)
  - M, 1869-1941 (Box 9, Folder 120-123)
  - Mather, Margaret Linton, 1904-1934 (Box 9, Folder 124)
  - N, 1902-1935 (Box 9, Folder 125-126)
  - O, 1901-1925 (Box 9, Folder 127)
  - P, 1803-1932 (Box 9, Folder 128-130)
  - Prescott, Winward C., 1906-1919, undated (Box 9, Folder 131)
  - R, 1862-1937 (Box 10, Folder 132-134)
  - S, 1890-1936 (Box 10, Folder 135-141)
  - Sattig, Gustave R., 1898-1941, undated (Box 10, Folder 142)
  - Seymour, George Dudley, 1894-1935, undated (Box 10, Folder 143-145)
  - Sherborn, C.W., 1897-1942, undated (Box 11, Folder 146-151)
  - T, 1894-1935 (Box 11, Folder 152-153)
  - U, 1901-1935 (Box 11, Folder 154-155)
  - V, 1895-1938 (Box 11, Folder 156-157)
  - Van Zandt, Margaret, 1895-1900 (Box 11, Folder 158)
  - Viner, G.H., 1897-1941, undated (Box 12, Folder 159-162)
  - W, 1893-1942 (Box 12, Folder 163-168)
  - Wall, Bernhardt, 1925-1942, undated (Box 12, Folder 169-170)
  - Woodbury, John P., 1894-1914, undated (Box 12, Folder 171)
  - Woodworth, L.C., 1891-1918, undated (Box 13, Folder 172-173)
  - Y-Z, 1913-1937 (Box 13, Folder 174-175)
- Invitations, 1890-1945; Series II
  This series contains invitations arranged in two sections: Hopson, William F. and Hopson, Ada W.
  Each section is arranged in alphabetical order by the name of the organization(s).
  - Hopson, William. F.
    - Acorn Club, 1899-1924, undated (Box 14, Folder 176-184)
    - Club of Odd Volumes, 1901-1914 (Box 14, Folder 185-188)
    - Club of Odd Volumes, 1915-1935, undated (Box 15, Folder 189-193)
    - Grolier Club, 1890-1920 (Box 15, Folder 194-199)
    - Grolier Club, 1921-1937, undated (Box 16, Folder 200-202)
    - Rowfant Club, 1898-1906 (Box 16, Folder 203-211)
    - Rowfant Club, 1907-1915 (Box 17, Folder 212-222)
    - Rowfant Club, 1916-1925 (Box 18, Folder 223-232)
    - Rowfant Club, 1926-1934 (Box 19, Folder 233-241)
  - Hopson, Ada W.
    - Rowfant Club, 1929-1935 (Box 19, Folder 242-244)
    - Rowfant Club, 1936-1939 (Box 20, Folder 245-256)
    - Rowfant Club, 1939-1943 (Box 21, Folder 257-267)
    - Rowfant Club, 1944-1945 (Box 22, Folder 268-269)
- Topical Files, 1830-1940; Series III
  This series contains material arranged in alphabetical order by record type. Miscellanea is arranged at the end of the series.
  - Account books, Undated (Box 23, Folder 270-271)
  - Genealogical papers, Undated (Box 24, Folder 272-274)
  - Notebooks, Undated (Box 24, Folder 275-277)
  - Notebooks, Undated (Box 25, Folder 278-283)
  - Notebooks, Undated (Box 26, Folder 284)
  - Photographs
    - Hopson, Ada Mabel Carter, Undated (Box 27, Folder 285)
    - Hopson, Orrin Lewis, Undated (Box 27, Folder 286)
    - Hopson, Susan Wilson, Undated (Box 27, Folder 287)
    - Hopson, William Fowler, Undated (Box 27, Folder 288-289)
    - Engravers, Undated (Box 27, Folder 290)
    - Family members, Undated (Box 27, Folder 291)
    - Miscellanea, Undated (Box 27, Folder 292-293)
  - Postcards, 1905-1934 (Box 28, Folder 294)
  - Printed material, 1830-1940, undated (Box 28, Folder 295-300)
  - Sketchbooks, Undated (Box 29, Folder 301-305)
  - Writings, Undated (Box 29, Folder 306)
  - Miscellancea
    - Bookplate lists, Undated (Box 30, Folder 307)
    - Family papers, Undated (Box 30, Folder 308)
    - Memorabilia, 1898-1927 (Box 30, Folder 309)
    - Obituaries, 1935 (Box 30, Folder 310)
    - Papers
      - Lodge, Hiram, 1900, 1936, undated (Box 30, Folder 311)
      - Rees, J. Rogers, 1900, 1903 (Box 30, Folder 312)
    - Seals, Undated (Box 30, Folder 313)
    - Miscellanea, Undated (Box 30, Folder 314)
- Oversize
  - "Der Fries im Thronsaale des Koeniglichen Schlosses in Dresden:" Al Fresco Gamalt von Eduard Bendeman (Gezeichnet and Radirt von Hugo Burkner), Undated (Box 31)
  - Sketches, watercolors (mostly unidentified), 1880, 1888, undated (Box 31)
  - Specifications for machinery for compressing, rounding, or pointing wires or rods to form pins, needles or other articles of metal: submitted to the Office of Patents by Messieurs Hopson and Brooks, 1867 (Box 32, Folder 54)
  - Indenture agreement between Messieurs Hopson and Brooks and Samuel Thomas, 1867 (Box 32, Folder 54)
  - Grant of a license to use patent between Orin Lewis Hopson and Messieurs Johnson and nephew, 1869 (Box 32, Folder 54)
  - Passport of William F. Hopson, 1904 (Box 32, Folder 54)